בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is ל"ז, Lamed Zayin, 37.
We pick up at the towards the bottom of ל"ו עמוד ב'
Lamed Vav Amud Bet and we were dealing with the whole story
about יוסף Yosef because it spoke about two people were מקדשי שם
שמים ברבים. mekaddeshe shem shamayim barabim. This got onto this because of
a whole discussion about יוסף Yosef and יהושע Yehoshua and how the
tribes were divided on הר גריזים Har Gerizim and הר עיבל, Har
Eival, so it spoke a little bit about יוסף. Yosef. So now
we're transitioning to a whole story about יוסף Yosef and יוסף Yosef
and יהושע Yehoshua were מקדשי שם שמים. mekaddeshe shem shamayim. יוסף Yosef
בסתר baseter and יהודה Yehudah ברבים. barabim. So the גמרא Gemara now
says the
following: תניא, Tanya, it's about ten lines before the lines get wide
towards the end of the line, about twelve lines before the lines
get wide, right above where it says אלה תולדות יעקב יוסף. Ele
toldos Yaakov Yosef. תניא, Tanya, היה ראוי יוסף לצאת ממנו י"ב שבטים,
haya raui Yosef latzes mimenu yud-bet shvatim, יוסף Yosef should have had
all twelve tribes come from him. Why not? Why was it, I
don't know, maybe equal to the brothers, not to exclude the brothers?
כדרך שיצאו מיעקב אביו, kederech sheyatze'u miYaakov aviv, שנאמר אלה תולדות יעקב
יוסף. shenemar Ele toldos Yaakov Yosef. So if there's this whole comparison,
these are the תולדות toldos of יעקב, Yaakov, יוסף, Yosef, which is
obviously a very interesting juxtaposition, right? The even if תולדות toldos means
the stories or the generation, but nevertheless you expect תולדות toldos also
to be a listing of the children and the only one it
mentions right afterwards is יוסף. Yosef. So that sounds like יוסף Yosef
should have been like a יעקב. Yaakov. אלא שיצא שכבת זרעו מבין
ציפורני ידיו. Ella sheyatza shichvas zaro mibein tzipornei yadav. But he went
at this moment, right, that the semen came out of his fingernails,
according to the story about how he had to resist אשת פוטיפר
Eishes Potifar at the last moment. So that was a loss of
at least ten of the twelve שבטים. shvatim. Now of course the
amazing thing is that the גמרא Gemara is talking about this as
an amazing act
of restraint and of קידוש שם שמים בסתר, kidush shem shamayim baseter,
but so sometimes I guess there's things are lost not due to
the fact that we're to blame, but just it's a reality
that we lose
opportunities or the question is
like what do they say the difference between a smart person and
a wise person is? A smart person can get out of situations
that a wise person never would have been in in the first
place.
So even if it's ויבא הביתה לעשות מלאכתו Vayavo habaisa la'asos melachto
might not have been
מלאכתו ממש, melachto mamash, I don't know, maybe he could have done
something a little bit more to prevent that from ever happened having
happened. Anyway, okay. ואף על פי כן יצאו מבנימין אחיו. Ve'af al
pi chen yatze'u miBinyamin achiv. ואף על פי כן, Ve'af al pi
chen, so even though he did not have ten children, יצאו מבנימין
אחיו, yatze'u miBinyamin achiv, בנימין Binyamin his brother had the remaining ten.
בנימין Binyamin had ten children. וכולן נקראו על שמו. Vekulan nikre'u al
shemo. They were all
named in honor of
יוסף. Yosef. שנאמר ובני בנימין בלע ובכר ואשבל: shenemar uvnei Binyamin Bela
v'Vacher v'Ashbel:
בלע, שנבלע בין האומות, Bela shenivla bein ha'umos, because he was swallowed
up amongst the other nations when he was sold יוסף, Yosef, when
he was sold into slavery. These all were representing, it's very powerful
also, because these were when יוסף Yosef was away, so I mean
we also always imagine בנימין Binyamin to have been like what, ten
years old or something, right? But he had all these children when
יוסף Yosef was away, and if you sort of think about that
as sort of longing after his brother יוסף Yosef and naming all
of his children because of this loss of יוסף, Yosef, it's very
powerful. So, בלע Bela, שנבלע בין האומות, shenivla bein ha'umos, ובכר, uVacher,
בכור לאמי היה, bechor l'imi haya, he was the firstborn at least
of my mother's children. ואשבל, v'Ashbel, ששבאו אל, sheshvao Kel, that God
has taken him captive, sort of seeing י-ה, Yah, השם Hashem in
it.
גרא, Gera, שגר באכסניות, shegar be'achsanyos, he dwelt in like lodging places,
meaning he's in exile. ונעמן, v'Naaman, שנעים ביותר, shenaim beyoser, he's very
pleasant.
אחי וראש, Achi v'Rosh, אחי הוא וראשי, achi hu v'roshi, my brother
and my head, my older brother. מופים וחופים, Mupim v'Chupim, הוא לא
ראה בחופתי ואני לא ראיתי בחופתו. hu lo ra'ah b'chupasi v'ani lo
ra'isi b'chupaso. I didn't see his wedding and he didn't see my
wedding. So that's חופה. chupa. It doesn't exactly say מופים Mupim except
that it sounds like חופה, chupa, so maybe it's sort of just
darshing the word twice. But רש"י Rashi says, רש"י Rashi says something
about מופים Mupim from the word פים, pim, מופי, mufi, שהיה פיו
כפי יעקב אבינו, shehaya piv k'pi Yaakov Avinu, בהלכות שקיבל משם ועבר.
b'halachos shekibel miShem v'Ever. So כמו פי k'mo pi is how רש"י
Rashi does it, which isn't in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. וארד, v'Ard,
שירד לבין האומות, sheyarad l'vein ha'umos, he went amongst the other nations.
העולם? ha'olam? Okay. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, וארד, v'Ard, שפניו דומים לורד,
shepanav domim l'vered, his face was like a rose. That doesn't exactly—everything
else was like historical and then this is bringing in this external
sort of image that we didn't have or information. Okay. What? נעמן
שנעים ביותר,
Naaman
shenaim
beyoser, that's true, that's
true, but this it echoes that. Okay. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, בשעה
שאמר לו פרעה ליוסף, b'shaa she'amar lo Paroh l'Yosef, ובלעדיך לא ירים
איש את ידו, uviladecha lo yarim ish es yado, other than you
no one else can raise their hand, you have full authority. אמרו
אצטגניני פרעה, Amru itzgninei Paroh, so the astrologers or the wise men
of פרעה Paroh said to him: עבד שלקחתו בעשרים כסף, Eved shelekachato
b'esrim kesef, a slave that was purchased with... of twenty talents of
silver, תמשילהו עלינו, tamsileihu aleinu, you'll make him master over us? אמר
להן גינוני מלכות אני רואה בו, amar lahen ginunei malchut ani ro'eh
bo, I see in him
the—what'd you say? The trappings. Oh, I thought it was more like
the aura of מלכות, malchut, Rashi says
גווני מלכות בחכמה גבורה ויופי, gvanei malchut bachochma gevura v'yofi, a little
bit echoing the ורד vered maybe idea. Anyway, that's the way I
read it. אני רואה בו. ani ro'eh bo. אמרו לו אם כן
יהא יודע בשבעים לשון, amru lo im ken yei yodeia b'shivim lashon,
let's test him. If he really is fit for such high office,
even a kingly office, you know, then he needs to know the
seventy languages. That shows that he's had a proper upbringing, he's fit
for this type of a status.
ואתא גבריאל, v'ata Gavriel, so what happened? ואתא גבריאל ולימדו שבעים לשון,
v'ata Gavriel v'limdo shivim lashon, so Gavriel came and taught Yosef seventy
languages. It's
sort of like the reverse of the whole story with Moshe, right?
With Pharaoh and Moshe the baby, right? Was it Gavriel who came
and made his hand move from the gold to the coals, and
that's how he became, you know, he became כבד לשון? kvad lashon?
So anyway, so here it's the same, except in the opposite direction,
preparing him for this encounter with the king. לא הוה קא גמיר.
lo hava ka gamir. Okay, so Gavriel taught him שבעים לשון. shivim
lashon. לא הוה קא גמיר, lo hava ka gamir, so he wasn't
able to learn it all so quickly. הוסיפו לו אות אחת משמו,
hosifu lo ot achat mishmo, tying back to the יהוסף Yehosef פסוק
pasuk we quoted
earlier, של הקדוש ברוך הוא shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu ולימד, v'limad, שנאמר
עדות ביהוסף שמו בצאתו על
ארץ מצרים.
shene'emar eidut bi'Yehosef samo b'tzeito al eretz
Mitzrayim. Okay, so—שפת לא ידעתי אשמע, sfat lo yadati eshma, בצאתו על
ארץ מצרים, b'tzeito al eretz Mitzrayim, exactly. It's interesting why they took
that out, because that's also—so I wasn't able to learn the language
and now I'm able to. Also, but this also ties back to
the whole point that Yosef that was קידש שם שמים בסתר, kidesh
shem shamayim b'seter, God הוסיף לו אות אחת משמו. hosif lo ot
achat mishmo. So here's another story of the—or you know, it's not
in contradiction to the other one, but the power of the אות
אחת משמו ot achat mishmo gave him the power to learn
the שבעים לשון. shivim lashon. ולמחר כל לישן דאשתעי פרעה בהדיה, ul'machar
kol lishon d'ishtai Paraoh bahadei, any language Pharaoh would try to talk
to him in, אהדר ליה, ahadar lei, so Yosef was able to
respond in the same language. So that was the test. Pharaoh started
switching languages and Yosef continued the conversation. אשתעי איהו בלשון הקודש ishtai
ihu bilshon hakodesh and Yosef talked to Pharaoh in Hebrew. לא הוה
קא ידע מאי הוה אמר, lo hava ka yada mai havai amar,
Pharaoh didn't know what this language was. אמר מאי הוה אמר, amar
mai havai amar, he didn't know what Yosef was saying. אמר ליה,
amar lei, so he said to Yosef, אגמרי, agmerei, so teach me
this, teach me this language. אגמרי, agmerei, he taught it to him.
ולא גמר, v'lo gamar, and now Pharaoh couldn't learn it.
Gavriel wasn't there to give him a helping hand. אמר ליה, amar
lei, so Pharaoh said to Yosef, אשתבע לי דלא מגלית, ishtaba li
d'lo megalis, swear to me that you will not reveal to anybody
that there's one language that I don't know, because Pharaoh is supposed
to be like a god and how could he not know a
language? ואשתבע ליה. v'ishtaba lei.
Oh, there you go. ואשתבע ליה. v'ishtaba lei. Right.
But I do wonder, I mean I just said it right now,
but I do wonder about that אות אחת משמו של הקדוש ברוך
הוא, ot achat mishmo shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu, right? This מלכות malchut
thing is very much tied also, but it's about godliness, right? Because
Pharaoh was seen as a god.
So Yosef had the real divine, he had the letter of God's
name, he had the לשון הקודש. lashon hakodesh. So Pharaoh here is
presenting himself as a god, but the one who really has that
element of
divinity is Yosef. Okay, so ואשתבע ליה, v'ishtaba lei, he swore to
him that he would not reveal to anyone. כי אמר ליה, ki
amar lei, now when Yosef said at the end of, you know,
after Yaakov died, אבי השביעני לאמר, avi hishpiani leimor, my father made
me take an oath to say that I will bring him out
of here and bury him in כנען, Kena'an, אמר ליה, amar lei,
so Pharaoh said to Yosef, זיל תשל אשבועתך, zil tishol ashvuatcha, so
what? Go do a התרת נדרים. hatarat nedarim. I learn נדרים nedarim
too. Go do a התר heter for your שבועה. shvua. אמר ליה,
amar lei, so he said back to him, alright, ואישל נמי אשבועתך,
v'eishul nami ashvuatach,
so while I'm doing my התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim I'll also get
a התר heter for the שבועה shvua I made to you, and
then I'll be able to reveal to people that you don't know
the language of Hebrew. ואף
על גב דלא ניחא ליה, va'af al gav d'lo nicha lei, so
even though Pharaoh was not happy with the situation, what was he
going to do? Yosef sort of said, you know, you want to
get me out of one שבועה, shvua, get out of the other
שבועה. shvua. אמר ליה עלה וקבור את אביך כאשר השביעך, amar lei
alei ukvor et avicha ka'asher hishbi'echa, fine, go do it. Now I
think part of what the מדרש Midrash is also picking up is
the כאשר השביעך. ka'asher hishbi'echa. Like that indicates that Pharaoh really only
agreed because of, because Yosef was under an oath. And so what
this also does is for—what is it, you know, why was Pharaoh
so respectful of the oath? So it sort of brings it in
how that idea of כי השביעך ki hishbi'echa has to be something
that was critically important to Pharaoh as well. תוספות Tosafot makes an
interesting question for those who remember our discussion in נדרים. nedarim. תוספות
Tosafot says, if you look at תוספות Tosafot ואישל נמי אשבועתך, v'ishul
nami ashvuatach, תוספות Tosafot says, ואם תאמר—sorry, v'im tomar ותימא—והלא לא היה
יכול לשאול על נדרו כי אם מדעתו של פרעה כמו מעשה ma'aseh,
דצדקיהו ונבוכדנצר דמעשה התם.
If you make an oath to somebody, not just to God, but
to someone, you can't do a התר heter on the שבועה shvua
without that person's
acknowledgment, awareness, maybe even
acquiescence.
Without Pharaoh's acquiescence.
No, he says— that I'll go and I'll get a התר heter
on the שבועה shvua that I'm going to make against you. Pharaoh
doesn't agree to that. Fine, you want me to get a התר
heter on my father's שבועה, shvua, I'll get a שבועה shvua while
I'm while I'm there I'll get a התר heter on your שבועה.
shvua. So you're not allowed to! You made a שבועה shvua to
me!
How'd you know that?
So,
so that's what תוספות Tosafot says. So תוספות Tosafot first tries to
work it out halachically and then he says,
ומיהו, umihu, if you go skip a few lines, because first maybe
it's בפניו befanav or שלא בפניו, shelo befanav, תמה לומר דנודר על
דעת חברו מתירים לו שלא מדעת חברו. teima lomar denoder al daat
chavero matirim lo shelo midaat chavero. It's impossible to say that. Whether
it was בפניו befanav or שלא בפניו, shelo befanav, impossible. ושמא אוקמינהו
אדיגזום, veshema okminehu adigeizum,
right he like, גיזום geizum doesn't just mean exaggeration, but you know,
he like, he scared him a bit with something that wasn't exactly
true. דעלמא דגזמוהו כך, dealma degazmuhu kach, that's what he threatened. Okay,
מיהו לא היה יכול להישאל עליו ולא ניחא ליה לפרעה. mihu lo
haya yachol lehishael alav velo nicha lei lePharaoh. He really wouldn't have
been able to do a התר, heter, but Pharaoh didn't know that.
So he said, you want me to get a התר heter on
one, so I'll get a התר heter on the other. I'm sorry,
what'd you say, Jenna?
Exactly.
He bluffed, exactly. There you go, exactly. Okay, okay now, that was
the story of יוסף Yosef and that it ended with the extra
letter of God's name, interestingly, right? Even though the end wasn't exactly
about the קידוש השם שמים. kiddush Hashem Shamayim.
Now, יהודה מהי? Yehuda mahi? Now יהודה Yehuda was קידוש השם שמים
ברבים, kiddush Hashem Shamayim berabbim, so he got his name was, he
was fully named after God. So again, if you ask me, פשט
pshat of that should have been our פרשה parsha where it was,
you know, ברבים berabbim and he owned up and he was מודה
modeh also the יהודה Yehuda and the מודה modeh ברבים berabbim and
so on, and that was יהודה Yehuda the person. Interestingly, the גמרא
Gemara is now going to turn the קידוש השם שמים kiddush Hashem
Shamayim to be ברבים berabbim to be יהודה Yehuda the tribe. יהודה
מהי? Yehuda mahi? What's the story of יהודה? Yehuda? דתניא, detanya, it
was taught in a ברייתא. braita. היה רבי מאיר אומר, haya Rabbi
Meir omer, כשעמדו ישראל על הים, kesheamdu Yisrael al hayam, when ישראל
Yisrael stood by the by the ים סוף, Yam Suf, היו שבטים
מנצחים זה עם זה, hayu shevatim menatzchim zeh im zeh, the tribes
were competing one against another. זה אומר אני יורד תחילה לים, zeh
omer ani yored techila layam, I'm going to go first. וזה אומר
אני יורד תחילה לים, vezeh omer ani yored techila layam, I'm going
to go first.
Okay, קפץ, kafatzt, so while everybody was
arguing, קפץ שבטו של בנימין וירד לים תחילה. kafatzt shivto shel Binyamin
veyarad layam techila. בנימין, Binyamin, while you guys were arguing, they went
ahead and they just and they just, you know, seized the opportunity.
Also it's convenient to be arguing who's going to go first because
then you don't have to actually be going first. Right.
All right. So שנאמר, shenemar, שם בנימין צעיר ורודם. sham Binyamin tzair
verodem. So there בנימין Binyamin the young one rules them. אל תקרי
ורודם, al tikri verodem, rules them, אלא רד ים, ela rad yam,
went down into the ocean. והיו שרי יהודה רוגמים אותם, vehayu sarei
Yehuda rogmem otam, and the and the officers of יהודה Yehuda were
stoning them, this is playing off the פסוק, pasuk, שנאמר, shenemar, שרי
יהודה רגמתם, sarei Yehuda rigmatam, and the the officers of יהודה Yehuda
stoned them. Because no, that was supposed to be our job, you
know, we're יהודה, Yehuda, we were supposed to go first, you snuck
in ahead of us.
Is that תהילים Tehillim talking about קריעת ים
סוף?
Kriat Yam
Suf?
לפיכך, lefichach, זכה בנימין הצדיק ונעשה אושפיזין לגבורה. zacha Binyamin hatzaddik venaaseh
ushpizin lagvura. But because בנימין Binyamin seized the opportunity and everybody else
was delaying, it doesn't matter who was supposed to go first, it
has to be done, they did it, they merited to be the
hosts of the Divine Presence. שנאמר ובין כתפיו שכן, shenemar uvein ktefav
shachan, going back to the ברכה, bracha, between God's Presence will dwell
between the between the shoulders of בנימין. Binyamin. Part of this is
because בנימין Binyamin and יהודה Yehuda's נחלה nachala sort of, you know,
directly juxtapose right at ירושלים Yerushalayim and according to חז"ל Chazal it's
like right at הר הבית. Har Habayit. And according to one understanding,
the place of the קודש קודשים Kodesh Kodashim actually falls into בנימין's
חלק Binyamin's chelek even though the rest of the בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash and הר הבית Har Habayit falls into יהודה's חלק. Yehuda's chelek.
So why is it that בנימין Binyamin gets that like, anyway it's
also very powerful, right? Because you have יוסף Yosef and, you know,
you know you have both שבטים shevatim represented,
the בני רחל bnei Rachel and בני לאה bnei Leah and so
on. Anyway, so why is it? I mean that's a, you know,
very powerful image that there's this, you know, two tribes right juxtaposed
there on the territory of הר הבית. Har Habayit. So here it
says, you know, that competition goes back. יהודה Yehuda wanted to be
first, should have been first, but
בנימין Binyamin seized the initiative, and that's what led to ultimately in
the end their greater connection to God. Okay, so that was the
version about בנימין Binyamin jumped first. That's not the version we know,
נחשון בן עמינדב. Nachshon ben Aminadav. If you take a look, תוספות
Tosafot brings down a nice מדרש. Midrash. תוספות Tosafot says, כך שנינו
בתוספתא ובמכילתין, kach shaninu baTosefta uvaMechiltin, משל למה הדבר דומה, mashal lema
hadavar domeh, למלך בשר ודם שהיו לו שני בנים. lemelech basar vadam
shehayu lo shenei vanim. He had two children, אחד גדול ואחד קטן,
echad gadol ve'echad katan, an older one and a younger one. אמר
לקטן, amar lakatan, he says to the younger one, העמידני עם הנץ
החמה, ha'imidani im hanetz hachama, wake me up at sunrise. אמר לגדול,
amar lagadol, העמידני בשלוש שעות, ha'imidani beshalosh shaot, wake me up in
time for קריאת שמע. Kriat Shema. ובא קטן להעמידו עם הנץ החמה,
uva katan leha'imido im hanetz hachama,
so the younger one came to wake him up for at sunrise,
ולא הניחו גדול, velo hanicho gadol, and
the older one didn't let him, go back to sleep. אמר לו
לא אמר לי אלא עד שלוש שעות, amar lo lo amar li
ela ad shalosh shaot, no, I'm not going to let you wake
him up at sunrise, he said we have to wait longer, we
have to wait till three hours into the day. ובא קטן אמר
לו לא אמר לי אלא עד הנץ החמה, uva katan amar lo
lo amar li ela ad hanetz hachama, no he wanted me to
wake him up now. מתוך שהיו עומדים צהובים, mitoch shehayu omdim tzehubim,
while they were standing, I don't know,
צהובים tzehubim means...
You were both trying to do the right thing. מה בני לקפח
שכרכם? Mah banai l'kape'ach s'charchem? I will not hold back your reward.
מה שכר נטל שבטו של בנימין שירד תחילה לים ששרתה שכינה בחלקו,
Mah sachar natul shivto shel Binyamin sheyarad techilah layam sheshartah Shechinah b'chelko,
שנאמר, shene'emar, etc., as they had the Divine Presence. מה שכר נטל
שבטו של יהודה? Mah sachar natul shivto shel Yehudah? זכה למלכות, zachah
l'malchus, שנאמר, shene'emar, סבבוני בכחש אפרים, savavuni b'chachash Ephraim, אין רד אלא
מלכות ein rad ela malchus because simple רד rad means kingship שנאמר
רודם, shene'emar rodam, ואין רודם אלא מלכות v'ein rodam ela malchus because
a simple רד rad means kingship שנאמר רודם, shene'emar rodam, not stoning
them. Okay, ויש אומרים, v'yeish omrim, the שוטר, shoter, דניאל, Daniel, ארגבנא,
argavana, ארגבנא argavana is ארגמן, argaman, yeah, like
the royal garment color, so anyway, the royal purple. So
according to the תוספתא, Tosefta, right, it has it that not like
it's all בנימין. Binyamin. Like it's suppose,
יהודה Yehuda was waiting for what they understood to be the right
time. יהודה Yehuda was saying it's not yet the time, and בנימין
Binyamin went and seized the initiative, and so both of them were
sort of doing the right thing, so they both got different types
of awards.
Yeah, it's interesting, if anything יהודה Yehuda should be punished for preventing,
you know, our version says there was,
yeah, I don't know if it says they were prevent, yeah, I
don't know if prevent, well, you know, yeah, like that was our,
that was our right to do that. Anyway, all right, moving on.
Yes, and the,
but the תוספתא Tosefta doesn't address that because the תוספתא Tosefta says
makes it not just that יהודה Yehuda was saying, hey, you stole
that, that was our מצוה mitzvah or our right, they were sort
of saying it's not yet time. According to the גמרא Gemara though,
it's a little difficult. Right, the גמרא Gemara doesn't spell out why
they were stoning, but yeah, you get the sense like, hey, that
was, we were supposed to do that.
Yeah, I didn't catch it, the מכילתא Mechilta has several different meanings.
First meaning מכילתא, Mechilta, our מסכת. masechet. So
but we don't know where that,
no, what we just read is the ברייתא braita in our מסכת,
masechet, but the
תוספתא, Tosefta, כדתניא ברייתא במכילתא, k'detanya braita b'Mechilta, what I'm sorry, you're
right. No, so you're right, he probably means the תוספתא. Tosefta. I
don't know why I was assuming it was a תוספתא. Tosefta.
I think he probably means the תוספתא, Tosefta, you can take a
look. Take a look at the תוספתא. Tosefta. That's what I'm guessing.
Okay, moving on.
Okay. אמר לו ר' יהודה, Amar lo Rabi Yehuda, ר' יהודה Rabi
Yehuda says לא כך היה מעשה, lo kach hayah ma'aseh, that wasn't
the story. אלא זה אומר אני ארד תחילה לים וזה אומר אני
ארד תחילה לים. ela zeh omer ani areid techilah layam v'zeh omer
ani areid techilah layam. This one says I'll go first, this one
says I'll go first.
קפץ נחשון בן עמינדב וירד לים Kafatz Nachshon ben Aminadav v'yarad layam
תחילה, techilah, שנאמר, shene'emar, סבבוני בכחש אפרים ובמרמה בית ישראל ויהודה עוד
רד עם אל. savavuni b'chachash Ephraim u'vmirmah beis Yisrael v'Yehudah od rad
im el. I was surrounded with deceit from אפרים Ephraim and from,
I don't know, deceit, trickery from
בית ישראל, beis Yisrael, ויהודה עוד רד עם אל, v'Yehudah od rad
im el, the nation of God. Okay, so רד rad means, you're
going to read it רד ים, rad yam, went down into the
nation or went down with
God, like, you know, because of his belief in God. ועליו מפורש
בקבלה, v'alav meforash b'kabalah, הושיעני אלקים כי באו מים עד נפש. hoshieini
Elokim ki va'u mayim ad nafesh. And now of course which just
makes it even more interesting is it's not like it split right
away, right? Because you know as you read the narrative in the
Torah, משה Moshe had to lift up his staff. How do you,
like, I'm sure you've ever asked somebody, wait a minute, how do
you square the idea that נחשון בן עמינדב Nachshon ben Aminadav jumped
down and that משה Moshe raised the staff, which one caused the
ים yam to split? Right? So I'm not sure we always try
to square those. So the מדרש Midrash is squaring it. Says yeah,
he went down, but nothing was happening, so he was about to
drown. Okay? So he had so much faith, it's not like it
automatically his faith was rewarded. It looked like he was going to
drown, it looked like, you know, that, and he was saying God
save me, right? כי
באו מים עד נפש, ki va'u mayim ad nafesh, the waters have
reached, you know, my soul or my throat. טבעתי ביון מצולה, tavati
b'yevein mtzulah, I'm going to, I've been sunk into the deep mire.
ואין מעמד, v'ein ma'amad, I can't stand. אל תשטפני
שבולת מים ואל תבלעני מצולה, al tishtifeini shibolet mayim v'al tivaleini mtzulah,
don't let the, you know, the wellspring of water, not the wellspring,
whatever, you know, the rushing of the water drown me. באותה שעה
היה משה מאריך בתפילה, b'osah sha'ah hayah Moshe maarich bitfilah, so משה
Moshe was praying, God, God save the people, right? אמר לו הקדוש
ברוך הוא, amar lo HaKadosh Baruch Hu, ידידיי טובעים בים, yedidai tov'im
bayam, my beloved ones (interesting in the plural) are drowning in the
nation, in the sea, right? Which echoes the famous מדרש Midrash of,
right, מעשי ידיי טובעים בים ואתם אומרים שירה? ma'aseh yadai tov'im bayam
v'atem omrim shirah? So I wonder if that's how come the plural
came here. Because it should have been ידידי, yedidi, but ידידיי, yedidai,
טובעים בים ואתה מאריך בתפילה לפני? tov'im bayam v'atah maarich bitfilah l'fanai?
You're praying before me? אמר לפניו רבונו של עולם ומה בידי לעשות?
amar l'fanav Ribbono Shel Olam u'mah b'yadi la'asos? What do you mean
are you praying before me? How God, what am I supposed to
do? Yes, that's what I do when they're drowning is I pray!
אמר לו, amar lo, you know what? Do, don't just pray. דבר
אל בני ישראל ויסעו, daber el B'nei Yisrael v'yisau, ואתה הרם את
מטך ונטה את ידך על הים ובקעהו. v'atah harem es matchah u'netay
es yadcha al hayam u'vka'eihu. And you know, no, just go forward,
lift up your, you know, your staff and split. So this is
extremely powerful, which I don't think is often appreciated. Meaning I think
every, all the school kids know the נחשון בן עמינדב Nachshon ben
Aminadav story. By the way, I think the reason that this story
survives, you know, or the one that we talk about rather than
the בנימין Binyamin one... because this one personalized it. Like say oh
the tribe of בנימין Binyamin went in, it's very abstract, it's not
powerful. To think that there's a single person who had faith and
jumped in like that's something that could be like inspiring and a
model. What does it mean? Right?
And the whole tribe followed.
So maybe that's the whole tribe followed and that's why they were
that's why they're but no, I'm saying the reason I think this
story is the powerful one that gets taught is because it's about
an individual having faith. Okay, but it's actually even much more powerful
than that, because first of all, the גמרא's Gemara picking up the
גמרא's Gemara picking up on on on you know, a very difficult
פסוק, pasuk, right? That God says, מה תצעק אלי דבר אל בני
ישראל ויסעו. Ma titzak elai daber el Bnei Yisrael veyisau. What are
you doing crying out to me? Just go forward. What are you
doing crying out to me? Like משה Moshe is awaiting instructions. What's
he supposed to do? He's praying, he's awaiting instructions. And at some
level, just פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim is God saying, you
know what? There's a time for prayer and there's a time to
wait to hear from me exactly what you're supposed to do, and
then there's a time to just know what you're supposed to do
and just go forward. You know, don't wait to hear it from
me, don't pray, just do what you have to you know, do
what you know deep down you have to get done. So the
power here is who knew that? נחשון בן עמינדב Nachshon ben Aminadav
knew that. He didn't have to wait for instruction. He deep down
knew if this is what's happening, obviously God wants us to go
into the ocean, right? So I think that's very powerful. Right. Ultimately,
but I'm still saying it's very powerful to have to see that
as sort of really echoed or echoing the דבר אל בני ישראל
ויסעו, daber el Bnei Yisrael veyisau, really making I think an important
point about faith and about what in some level I think at
some level, not that the נחשון Nachshon story is פשט, pshat, but
the point here is that it's the פשט pshat in the פסוק
pasuk about just have the faith, take the leap of faith, jump,
don't, you know, just move forward. You don't know, stop praying, move
forward. The other interesting thing is that the פסוק pasuk by ים
סוף Yam Suf is ויאמינו בה' ובמשה עבדו, Vaya'aminu b'Hashem uv'Moshe avdo,
right? And what does it mean? Before that they didn't believe? Like
they saw, you know, what do they say? They saw the miracle,
they saw all that, they didn't believe? So there's a sense there
of אמונה emunah not as abstract faith or believing that God exists,
right? But it's having real live faith in God. So if this
was like a show of אמונה, emunah, right? So it's your you're
willing to put your faith in God and do something, so that
actually, you know, again, personalizing it very much with נחשון Nachshon who
was prepared to do it even before the the the ים Yam
had split. Yes, Joe, you wanted to
I was thinking about it's noticed it wasn't supposed to be spending
time praying there.
איוב Iyov is criticized in our tradition for never praying in a
in a in a yeah,
I mean משה Moshe prayed 99 percent of the time. I'm not
saying he never prayed, I'm saying there are times where stop praying,
like this is not the time for prayer, this is the time
for action.
Yeah, there must be a parallel to this somewhere. Unless I'm missing
it, where's נחשון's Nachshon name mentioned?
It's not. It's just that he was the head of יהודה Yehuda
and it wants to oh maybe, that could be. But this again,
it took פסוקים psukim קפץ
נחשון בן עמינדב אל הים
תחילה.
Kafatz Nachshon ben Aminadav el
hayam techilah. Oh yeah. No, no, it's in this story. Oh I
thought you were just saying where they're getting it from the פסוק.
pasuk. Yeah, there it is, ten lines from the top, קפץ נחשון
בן עמינדב. Kafatz Nachshon ben Aminadav. But it's taking it because it's
personalizing it, right? It could have been the tribe of יהודה Yehuda
like you had the tribe of בנימין, Binyamin, and this story chooses
to personalize it in the person of נחשון. Nachshon.
Yes, this is like one of my favorite דברי תורה divrei Torah
of all time, the קוצקער רבי Kotzker Rebbe said on this that
these two opinions are not so in disagreement and it sort of
harks to what you said. So one was like, you know, a
time for talk, right? Everyone, you know, like they were all talking,
right? When they were fighting, who's going to go it's a time
for action, right? In other words, but then like someone actually, you
know what I'm saying? Like it could still be two different sides
of the same coin, if you get what I'm saying.
No, because what he's trying to say, both בנימין Binyamin went down
first and נחשון Nachshon לא פליגי אהדדי. lo pligi ahadedi. In other
words, he's saying לא פליגי אהדדי, lo pligi ahadedi, in other words
I agree with you, when it was time for the theoretical debate
everyone was was was was saying איני יורד תחילה לים, איני יורד
תחילה לים. Iny yored techilah layam, iny yored techilah layam. But the
actual when it came down to מעשה, you know...
okay, alright, that's just a nice way of emphasizing that. Okay, alright,
so moving on,
okay, ועתה הרם את מטך
ונטה את ידך, Ve'atah harem et mitcha uneteh et yadecha, just go
forward, have faith. וזכו יהודה לעשות ממשלה בישראל, Vezachu Yehuda la'asot memshalah
b'Yisrael, and because they took this leadership role, right? It's also interesting
about the difference between leadership and אמונה. emunah. And if you think
about that, that's also the יהודה Yehuda not בנימין Binyamin story, but
the יהודה-יוסף Yehuda-Yosef story. Right, יוסף Yosef was coming up in all
the פרשיות, parshiyot, יוסף Yosef is going to say, you know, יוסף
Yosef is like waiting for God to work through him. Right, the
most initiative יוסף Yosef takes is he says, you know, והזכרתני אל
פרעה והוצאתני מן הבית הזה, Vehizkartani el Paroh vehotzeitani min habayit hazeh,
but יוסף Yosef is like, no, God is doing it, God is
working through even when the brothers sort of, you know, take responsibility,
יוסף Yosef says, no, don't feel bad, it's all God's plan, it's
all God doing it, which is very good from a religious perspective,
but you know, you don't want your leader to you don't want
your leader to say, don't worry, it's all God's doing. Right? You
want your leader to say the buck stops here, right, which is
what יהודה Yehuda says, right? אנכי אערבנו, Anochi e'ervenu, it's my responsibility,
I'm going to do it. So the first story has בנימין, Binyamin,
I sort of see בנימין Binyamin and יוסף Yosef together there, right,
as sort of, you know, it's all about the זכות zechut of
the faith, it was an act of faith and the reward was
God's presence. With this, it was also an act of faith, I
mean that was the whole point I was making before, but it
was also an act of leadership. The zechus זכות zechus was that
they were zochu זכו zochu l'mimshalah לממשלה. l'mimshalah. So okay, shene'emar שנאמר,
shene'emar, haysah
היתה haysah yehuda יהודה yehuda lekodsho לקדשו, lekodsho, yisroel ישראל yisroel mamshelosov
ממשלותיו. mamshelosov. Yehuda was for God's holy one, again interesting now the
holiness, and Yisroel God's for God's queenship. Mah tam haysah yehuda lekodsho
yisroel mamshelosov מה טעם היתה יהודה לקדשו ישראל ממשלותיו? Mah tam haysah
yehuda lekodsho yisroel mamshelosov? Mishum dehayam ra'ah vayanos משום דהים ראה וינס
Mishum dehayam ra'ah vayanos because the ocean turned back because of these
actions of Yehuda. Again it was actions of Yehuda followed by the
actions of Moshe. By the way, it's also another important point about
faith, your faith isn't always immediately answered, right? Looks like he was
about to drown. Tanya תניא, Tanya, sometimes you need people to come
with you in the journey. Tanya Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer תניא
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר: Tanya Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer: iy
efshar lomar levi lemattah אי אפשר לומר לוי למטה. iy efshar lomar
levi lemattah. Now after that really fun stuff, we're back to Har
Gerizim הר גריזים Har Gerizim and Har Eival הר עיבל Har Eival
which is also fun. Anyway, okay, so where how are the tribes
divided?
So now he's dealing with a problem. Iy efshar lomar levi lemattah
אי אפשר לומר לוי למטה, iy efshar lomar levi lemattah, you can't
say that Levi was below the two mountains at the foot of
the mountains, shekevar ne'emar lemalah שכבר נאמר למעלה shekevar ne'emar lemalah because
basically the problem is that in the division of the tribes in
the Torah תורה, Torah, Levi is on Har Gerizim הר גריזים. Har
Gerizim. In the story in Yehoshua, it says the Kohanim כהנים Kohanim
and the Levi'im לויים Levi'im were in the center with the Aron
ארון. Aron. Below, right? So how you going to reconcile it? Shekevar
ne'emar lemalah שכבר נאמר למעלה, shekevar ne'emar lemalah, ve-iy efshar lomar lemalah
ואי אפשר לומר למעלה, ve-iy efshar lomar lemalah, you can't say they
were above like it is in the Torah תורה, Torah, shekevar ne'emar
למטה, shekevar ne'emar lemattah, it says in Yehoshua that they were below.
Ha ketzad הכיצד? Ha ketzad? How you reconcile it? Zikne kehuna ve-leviya
lemattah זקני כהונה ולויה למטה, Zikne kehuna ve-leviya lemattah, so the elders
of the kehuna and leviya were below with the Aron ארון, Aron,
vehash'ar lemalah והשאר למעלה vehash'ar lemalah the rest of the tribe was
above. Okay. Rabbi Yoshi omer רבי יאשיה אומר: Rabbi Yoshi omer: kol
harauy lesharet lemattanoh כל הראוי לשרת למטה, kol harauy lesharet lemattanoh, everybody
that could be in the divine service was between the ages of
like 30 and 50, which is the age of sherut שירות sherut
for Levi, was below and then, vehash'ar lemalah והשאר למעלה vehash'ar lemalah
and the rest were above. Rebbi omer רבי אומר: Rebbi omer: elu
ve-elu lemattah אלו ואלו למטה. elu ve-elu lemattah. They were both below,
hem omdim הם עומדים. hem omdim. Everybody was below. So what does
happen? Because it wasn't just Levi that was below. All the twelve
tribes were below. Here he's dealing with another problem. Right? By Moshe
it says eleh ya'amdu al har gerizim אלה יעמדו על הר גריזים
eleh ya'amdu al har gerizim and by Yehoshua it says mul har
gerizim מול הר גריזים mul har gerizim that they stood by at
the foot of the mountains mul har gerizim מול הר גריזים. mul
har gerizim. So it's actually going to reconcile this contradiction in favor
of the pesukim פסוקים pesukim of Yehoshua and say that it was
more mul than it was al. Okay and therefore elu ve-elu
אלו ואלו, elu ve-elu,
yeah all the tribes, everything was below. You don't have to reconcile
it. You only have to reconcile it if you think that half
of them were on the mountain. But no, half of them were
to one side of the mountain, if there's a valley and there's
two mountains, half are on this side and half are on that
side at the foot of the different mountains but ultimately they're all
in the middle. Okay. Elu ve-elu lemattah hayu omdim אלו ואלו למטה
היו
עומדים.
elu ve-elu
lemattah hayu omdim.
Hafchu peneihem klapei
har gerizim הפכו פניהם כלפי הר גריזים hafchu peneihem klapei har gerizim
and then everybody turned to Har Gerizim הר גריזים. Har Gerizim. It
doesn't just have the bracha ברכה, bracha, the or the amen אמן
amen by the people standing on Har Gerizim הר גריזים. Har Gerizim.
Everybody looks towards Har Gerizim הר גריזים Har Gerizim and upatchei bivracha
ופתחו בברכה upatchei bivracha and they gave the bracha ברכה. bracha. Klapei
har eival כלפי הר עיבל klapei har eival then they all turned
around and faced Har Eival הר עיבל, Har Eival, upatchei biklala ופתחו
בקללה upatchei biklala and they gave the klala קללה. klala. Okay. Mai
מאי, mai, so that's true, mai al al מאי על על? mai
al al? What does it mean by in the pesukim פסוקים pesukim
in Devarim דברים Devarim where it says eleh ya'amdu al har gerizim
אלה יעמדו על הר גריזים? eleh ya'amdu al har gerizim? Besamuch בסמוך,
besamuch, it means near Har Gerizim הר גריזים. Har Gerizim. Kiditanya כדתניא:
kiditanya: venasata al hamareches levona zaka ונתת על המערכת לבונה זכה. venasata
al hamareches levona zaka. You shall put on the sort of on
the structure of the bread there the shelves you should put levona
לבונה, levona, the frankincense. Rabbi omer רבי אומר: Rabbi omer: al besamuch
על בסמוך. al besamuch. It doesn't mean literally on the shelves of
the bread you put the levona לבונה, levona, no it means near
them, right in the space between like the two shelvings, the two...
shene'emar שנאמר... shene'emar... ata omer al besamuch o eino ela al mamash
אתה אומר על בסמוך או אינו אלא על ממש? ata omer al
besamuch o eino ela al mamash? Maybe it literally means on. Keshehu
omer כשהוא אומר: keshehu omer: vesakota al ha'aron וסכות על הארון vesakota
al ha'aron and that the paroches פרוכת paroches would shade on the
Aron ארון. Aron. Hevei omer al besamuch הוי אומר על בסמוך. hevei
omer al besamuch. Not literally on top of the Aron ארון Aron
because it's vertical, it's not a horizontal awning, so it means it's
nearby, not literally on. Okay.
By the way, it's interesting
also and if you think visually the more powerful image I think
is the image you get when you read the Torah תורה Torah
is that there's a group below, they turn, six tribes on here
say
amen אמן amen and they're standing on a barren mountain that represents
klala קללה, klala, or we'll start with the curse, they're standing on
a lush mountain that's bracha ברכה bracha and they say baruch ברוך
baruch and they all say amen אמן, amen, it means like if
you do the right thing you're going to be blessed like this,
right? And then you turn to the other way and they're arur
ארור arur and say amen אמן amen and you have that visual
like these tribes on this mountain which represents something like looking at
it and then looking at it. I don't know, somehow it's not
the same choreography
but anyway but what you gain by it is that you have
everybody part of the process. It's not just half of the people
are saying amen אמן, amen, it's like everybody's saying everything and everybody
sort of is owning it. Now the...
just to describe one was lush and one was...
No, but that's the reality. I'm just bringing that in to help
us appreciate the image of what's going on. Okay, maybe. I did
not make that up, that's actually true, but it's not said in
the pesukim פסוקים. pesukim. Okay, so okay. Anyway
and Tosfos תוספות Tosfos points out,
one
minute... no... Okay, there's another point that I think רש״י Rashi made
about,
somebody points out, maybe it's coming up. Oh, wait, I think it's
coming up, that actually the פסוקים psukim do make it sound, it
says וענו כל העם ואמרו אמן, v'anu kol ha-am v'amru amen, וענו
כל העם. v'anu kol ha-am. So even in the way the תורה
Torah describes it, you don't have just the tribes there saying אמן
amen like the תורה Torah also has like everybody being involved. Okay,
but still somehow there's something in my mind more powerful of the
image of the different tribes on the mountain than just having everybody
below. But anyway, and so this has everybody below, everybody saying it,
everybody I guess saying אמן amen to their own ברכה, bracha, I
don't know. But anyway, but in the תורה Torah it's clear that
everybody does say אמן. amen. Now, הפכו פניהם כלפי הר גריזים ופתחו
בברכה. haphchu pnehem klapei Har Grizim u'petchu b'bracha. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabanan:
ברוך בכלל ברוך בפרט, baruch bikhlal baruch biprat, ארור בכלל ארור בפרט.
arur bikhlal arur biprat. Okay, so basically if you go ahead, right,
so the first, you know, it says ארור אשר לא יקים את
דברי התורה הזאת לעשות אותם, arur asher lo yakim et divrei ha-Torah
hazot la'asot otam, the last one. So that's the כלל, klal, like
everything is included. Not just the ones we've said, anybody who's not
going to do anything is בכלל ארור. bikhlal arur. Okay, it's interesting
how you read אשר לא יקים את דברי התורה הזאת לעשות אותם,
asher lo yakim et divrei ha-Torah hazot la'asot otam, does it mean
who doesn't do anything, who doesn't establish the whole תורה, Torah, who
undermines the entire תורה, Torah, you know? Anyway, but this is sort
of reading it as a כלל, klal, it covers anything. And then
you have the specific things that are mentioned. Okay, now you have
the ארורים, arurim, but it says you also give a blessing. Well,
what's the blessing? So the understanding is it's the reverse of the
ארורים. arurim. If it's ארור אשר לא יקים, arur asher lo yakim,
it's ברוך אשר יקים. baruch asher yakim. ארור שוכב עם כל בהמה,
arur shochev im kol behemah, ברוך אשר לא שוכב עם כל בהמה.
baruch asher lo shochev im kol behemah. Okay, so that would be—so
you had the general ברוכים bruchim and the specific ones, and the
general ארורים arurim and the specific ones. Okay, now: ללמוד וללמד לשמור
ולעשות. lilmod u'lelamed lishmor ve'la'asot. Also for every מצוה, mitzvah, you know
how sort of like on the הגדה Haggadah when we sort of
say, you know, כל מכה ומכה שהביא הקדוש ברוך הוא היתה של
ארבע מכות, kol maka u'maka she-hevei ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu haya shel arba
makot, every מכה maka had four dimensions, so every מצוה mitzvah has
four dimensions. What's the four dimensions of every מצוה? mitzvah? To learn
and to teach, to observe I guess and to do it. Interestingly
how both the observing and the doing, you know, sometimes observing is
associated with לא תעשה, lo ta'asei, doing with עשה. ta'asei. Anyway רש״י
Rashi quotes the פסוקים psukim where it says, you know, ולמדתם אותם
ושמרתם לעשותם, u'lemadetem otam u'shmartem la'asotam, you know, how everything is ללמוד
וללמד. lilmod u'lelamed. So that's true, so everything, every כלל ברכה klal
bracha has two—has a ברוך baruch and an ארור, arur, and really
everything has four ברוכים bruchim and four ארורים arurim if you think
about it, right? Because for every מצוה mitzvah there's four things you
should be blessed for: blessed for ללמוד וללמד לשמור ולעשות lilmod u'lelamed
lishmor ve'la'asot and there're four things you should be cursed for, right,
if you don't do it: ללמוד וללמד לשמור ולעשות. lilmod u'lelamed lishmor
ve'la'asot. So everything has eight aspects
to every single one.
Reminds me of the הגדה.
Haggadah. Yeah, exactly. All right, ארבע וארבע, arba ve-arba, four plus four,
ארבע, arba, so that's four. No, no. ארבע וארבע הוי שמנה. arba
ve-arba havei shmoneh. Okay, so that's eight. So everything has eight dimensions:
four ברוכים bruchim and four ארורים. arurim.
And then four for each.
שמנה ושמנה הוי שש עשרה. shmoneh ve-shmoneh havei sheish-esrei. Now you have
eight plus eight, you have
your—you have your eight for the כלל klal and your eight for
the פרט, prat, so you really have 16. Now what we're going
to do is count up all the פרטים, pratim, but okay, whatever,
you've got 16 here בריתות britot is the concept.
Wait, can you just go one more time?
Because every מצוה mitzvah has four ברכות brachot and four ארורים, arurim,
right? ברוך baruch for ללמוד וללמד לשמור ולעשות. lilmod u'lelamed lishmor ve'la'asot.
So if we're talking about כלל klal and פרט, prat, you combine
the two eights and you get 16. Okay, שש עשרה. sheish-esrei. וכן
בסיני וכן בערבות מואב ve-khein be-Sinai ve-khein be-Arvot Moav and similarly they
did
similar—remember a sense of a ברית, brit, the גמרא Gemara before, you
know, we don't have the ברכות brachot and the קללות, klalot, but
now it's sort of shifting the framing to not just be about
a ברכה bracha and a קללה, klala, but it's a ברית. brit.
So there's like, you know, it's being sealed with these sort of
16 things. So where else do we have a sense of a
ברית? brit? We have it in ערבות מואב Arvot Moav and in
סיני. Sinai. שנאמר: she-ne'emar: אלה דברי הברית אשר צוה ה' את משה
לבני ישראל בהר סיני, eileh divrei ha-brit asher tziva Hashem et Moshe
li-vnei Yisrael be-Har Sinai, right, what is it... מלבד הברית אשר כרתי
אתם בחורב. milvad ha-brit asher karati itam be-Chorev. Okay, so... וכתיב: u-chtiv:
ושמרתם את דברי הברית הזאת. u-shmartem et divrei ha-brit hazot. Okay,
so anyway, so you have the ברית brit at מואב Moav and
the ברית brit at חורב Chorev and this which is seen as
a ברית brit and each one
there are 16 dimensions. נמצא מ״ח בריתות. nimtza mem-chet britot. So it's
sort of making this shift from ברוך baruch to a ברית, brit,
the ברוך baruch and the ארור, arur, but each aspect of ברוך
baruch and an ארור arur represents a form of a ברית. brit.
So there are מ״ח בריתות על כל מצוה ומצוה mem-chet britot al
kol mitzvah u-mitzvah for every מצוה mitzvah in the תורה, Torah, right?
Because you had 16 ברוך baruch and ארור arur whatever, it's 16,
16, 48. Okay, again, the math—you can figure out the math, it's
a little—like, does that really work, like why aren't we mentioning the
פרטים pratim specifically and anyway fine, we won't worry about that.
Why does it say ארבע arba three times and not four?
ארבע, arba, that makes four. ארבע וארבע הוי שמנה, arba ve-arba havei
shmoneh, שמנה ושמנה הוי שש עשרה. shmoneh ve-shmoneh havei sheish-esrei. And it's
twenty-nine thousand four
hundred... we're getting there. Okay, רבי שמעון מוציא הר גריזים. Rabbi Shimon
motzi Har Grizim. First we're going to have a very interesting and
important debate. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no, no, no, הר גריזים
Har Grizim wasn't one of the בריתות britot והר עיבל, ve-Har Eival,
ומכניס אהל מועד שבמדבר. u-machnis Ohel Moed she-ba-midbar. If you want to
say three times that there was a ברית, brit, it was הר
סיני, Har Sinai, אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, וערבות מואב. ve-Arvot Moav. Now
of course the interesting thing is because we've switched the discourse or
the language, the theme to ברית, brit, we're able to take out
גריזים, Grizim, הר גריזים והר עיבל. Har Grizim ve-Har Eival. You realize
we started with the presence of ברוך, baruch, right? How many ברוךs
baruch and how many ארורs? arur But now we're really saying that
that just represents a dimension of a ברית. brit. Once it's a
dimension of a ברית, brit, then since when is הר גריזים Har
Gerizim and הר עיבל Har Eival the עיקר ברית? ikar brit? The
עיקר ברית ikar brit that gets described in the תורה, Torah, right,
is סיני Sinai and חורב Chorev and whatever happened to all the
מצוות mitzvot that were given at אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. So those
are the three loci, locai of the ברית. brit. Forget that, forget
הר גריזים Har Gerizim and הר עיבל, Har Eival, that's just ברוך
baruch and ארור. arur. These are the ברית. brit. Okay. וקא מיפלגי
בהני תנאי, ve-ka mipalgi behani tannai, and it's following the debate of
the תנאים, tannaim, דתניא, detanya, it was taught in a ברייתא, braita,
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael אומר omer כללות נאמרו בסיני klalot ne'emru be-Sinai,
פרטות pratot באהל מועד. be-Ohel Moed. The general principles were said at
הר סיני Har Sinai and the specific ones were said at אהל
מועד. Ohel Moed. So what does רש"י Rashi gives an example about
that? כללות נאמרו בסיני, klalot ne'emru be-Sinai, just look at רש"י, Rashi,
second line in and the third line in the narrow line, second
line: בסתם
נאמרה be-stam ne'emra תורה Torah בסיני be-Sinai ולא נתפרשה ve-lo nitparsha בו
bo כגון kegon בסיני be-Sinai נאמר ne'emar וזבחת עליו את עולותיך ואת
שלמיך ve-zavachta alav et olotecha ve-et shelamecha ולא פירש ve-lo peirash מתן
דמים matan damim כיצד. keitzad. How do you do the sacrifice but
where are all the details?
הקטרת אימורין haktarat emurin כיצד, keitzad, הקטרת אימורין haktarat emurin והפשט וניתוח
ve-hafshat ve-nituach הכל לעולה, ha-kol le-olah, ובספר ויקרא באהל מועד פירשה. u-ve-Sefer
Vayikra be-Ohel Moed peirshah. So basically everything that happened in the תורה
Torah after אהל מועד Ohel Moed after סיני. Sinai. By the way,
interesting, because to help this work רש"י Rashi doesn't limit סיני Sinai
to the עשרת הדיברות, Aseret HaDibrot, right? The פסוק pasuk of וזבחת
עליו את עולותיך ואת שלמיך, ve-zavachta alav et olotecha ve-et shelamecha, right,
that's like in
the set—where's that? That's at the end of משפטים, Mishpatim, right? No,
but
where is וזבחת עליו? ve-zavachta alav? No, where is וזבחת עליו? ve-zavachta
alav? Hold on.
Because it is going to be harder if you limit it to
the עשרת הדיברות Aseret HaDibrot getting that to be the כלל. klal.
The question is you also include משפטים, Mishpatim, because if you read
the פשט pshat of the פסוקים, psukim, right, משה Moshe doesn't leave
הר סיני, Har Sinai, gets the עשרת הדיברות Aseret HaDibrot and then
ואלה המשפטים אשר תשים לפניהם ve-eleh ha-mishpatim asher tasim lifneichem and he's
still up there at הר סיני. Har Sinai. And then at the
end of משפטים, Mishpatim, משה Moshe comes down and he reads—what does
he do at the end of משפטים? Mishpatim? Anybody knows what משה
Moshe does when he comes down at the end of משפטים?
Mishpatim? At the end of משפטים, Mishpatim, yeah, there's a ברית. brit.
He writes all of the דברי ה' ואת כל המשפטים, divrei Hashem
ve-et kol ha-mishpatim, which is the עשרת הדיברות Aseret HaDibrot and all
of פרשת משפטים parshat Mishpatim and he writes it in a book
and it's a ספר הברית Sefer HaBrit and he's כורת הברית koreit
ha-brit with בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. That's the real כריתת הברית. kritat
ha-brit. So if you want to have the כללות klalot at סיני,
Sinai, it makes more sense if you're allowed those כללות klalot to
include, if you have everything בכלל, be-klal, it makes more sense if
you want those כללות klalot to include, what do you call it,
to include
all of פרשת משפטים. parshat Mishpatim. But
רש"י Rashi is—no, רש"י Rashi is actually just the few פסוקים psukim
at the end of יתרו. Yitro. אלוהי כסף מזבח אדמה תעשה לי
וזבחת עליו את עולותיך ואת שלמיך. elohei chesef mizbach adamah ta'aseh li
ve-zavachta alav et olotecha ve-et shelamecha. Okay, so question is what does
it mean the כללות klalot and everything else is an explication of
it. Now, if you do say that it's limited—it doesn't include all
of פרשת משפטים, parshat Mishpatim, but that includes—it's just fundamentally the עשרת
הדיברות Aseret HaDibrot till the end of יתרו. Yitro. This leads to
a very early idea in rabbinic sort of thought
that all the תרי"ג מצוות taryag mitzvot can somehow be incorporated under
the עשרת הדיברות. Aseret HaDibrot. That any מצוה mitzvah to some degree
is a certain application of one of the עשרת הדיברות. Aseret HaDibrot.
This goes all the way back to פילון. Philo. I mean פילון,
Philo, you know, it's a scheme of organization of the תרי"ג מצוות
taryag mitzvot all the way to sort of see that—it also raises
the question: what's the distinctiveness of the עשרת הדיברות? Aseret HaDibrot? Are
they more important than other things? So seeing them as categories and
that
everything else as פרטים pratim within those כללות. klalot Okay, so that's
one approach. כללות klalot. נאמרו ne'emru בסיני, be-Sinai either including through the
end of משפטים Mishpatim or the עשרת הדיברות. Aseret HaDibrot. Everything else
in the תורה Torah is an explication of that. ופרטו באהל מועד.
u-prato be-Ohel Moed. Wait a minute. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר: omer:
לא, כללות ופרטות נאמרו בסיני. lo, klalot u-pratot ne'emru be-Sinai. Everything was
given in הר סיני, Har Sinai, okay? ונשנו באהל מועד, ve-nishnu be-Ohel
Moed, and it was all repeated. So even if you have details
that the תורה Torah describes that God in ויקרא Vayikra said here's
the specifics of the עולה olah and the שלמים shlamim or whatever,
it was already given in הר סיני. Har Sinai. It was just
being repeated. Why the תורה Torah just chooses to write that this
was down in the context אהל מועד Ohel Moed and that it
doesn't say הר סיני? Har Sinai? Okay, I don't know. But nevertheless,
every—all the details were already told at הר סיני. Har Sinai. ונשתלשו
בערבות מואב. ve-nishtalshu be-arvot Moav. And then it was all said the
third time at ערבות מואב. Arvot Moav. So, if you say there
were two בריתות britot plus הר גריזים Har Gerizim and הר עיבל,
Har Eival, or were there three בריתות? britot? So if everything was—if
the details were spelled out in אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, it's all
part of the same ברית, brit, right? Because the ברית brit that—the
whole package you don't get done with until the end of אהל
מועד. Ohel Moed. So that's one—that approach has one ברית brit of
סיני Sinai and אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, ברית brit number two ערבות
מואב, Arvot Moav, and ברית brit number three הר גריזים Har Gerizim
and הר עיבל. Har Eival. Whereas רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, "No,
all three: הר סיני Har Sinai everything, אהל מועד Ohel Moed everything,
and ערבות מואב Arvot Moav everything." It's by the way interesting again
it's a רבי עקיבא-רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Akiva-Rabbi Yishmael debate and to what
degree to see this as a profound theological debate that ties in
maybe to some of their hermeneutics, right, where if רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva wants everything straight from God—I mean אהל מועד Ohel Moed is
also straight. less that immediate the immediacy of הר סיני Har Sinai
and everything is there, does that lead to his sort of hermeneutic
of being דרשינג darshing every single letter, you know, and so on
as opposed to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael that has more דיברה תורה
כלשון בני אדם dibra Torah kilshon bnai adam and if he sees
most of the תורה Torah is sort of given through God, you
know, from God, but in a slightly less immediate way, you know,
maybe some of their hermeneutics are tied into some of this theology.
Anyway, this is sort of a central part of Heschel's תורה מן
השמים, Torah Min Hashamayim, you know, sort of a masterpiece there. Yes.
So
your understanding that the כללות klalot are just the עשרת הדיברות Aseret
HaDibrot and the פרטות pratot are all the subsequent פסוקים? pesukim?
Well, that's I think a normal understanding, but I was suggesting that
it's תורה שבעל פה Torah SheBaal Peh as a model for תורה
שבעל פה. Torah SheBaal Peh.
That's I that's not what it's that's not what it's dealing with
now. What it's dealing with now is the no, I mean I'm
not saying you can't use that as a model. What it's dealing
with now is, first of all, the emphasis of ברית brit that
occurs at הר סיני. Har Sinai. And how do you explain, you
know, if הר סיני Har Sinai models for us the receiving of
the entire תורה, Torah, how do you explain the fact that you
don't have the whole תורה Torah there, that a lot of it
is said in the next three ספרים sefarim in the in the
תורה, Torah, you know? So the answer is either yes, get over
it, it's not all straight from הר סיני, Har Sinai, it's the
כפסקן משנו ונסעו, kefiskan mishnu venasau,
it was הר סיני Har Sinai all the way through.
Yes, yeah, you could
it's true, you could say that, I'm just saying that's look, I'm
not saying you can I that's not the standard understanding. I think
the standard reading is מעמד הר סיני, Maamad Har Sinai, the עשרת
הדיברות. Aseret HaDibrot. I was trying to include even משפטים Mishpatim in
it because the end of the ברית brit comes at the end
of משפטים. Mishpatim. Yeah, but it's not about this this is not
about about תורה שבעל פה. Torah SheBaal Peh. This is about תורה
שבכתב. Torah SheBichtav.
And do you see a nice parallel to that סוגיא sugia in
עירובין Eruvin where like they go into the אהל מועד Ohel Moed
and משה Moshe teaches them פרקו pirko and then they go out?
Like you have
a whole explication there what was going on.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. I mean, how does that fit into this? I
but I think that you're right, you should like put those two
next to each other and see what comes out of it. Okay,
so, okay, רבי שמעון בן יהודה איש כפר עכו אומר, Rabbi Shimon
ben Yehuda ish Kfar Akko omer, so I'm sorry, I skipped a
line. Okay, so that's that's the question about where the three בריתות
britot are. Everybody agrees there are three, but look, I think this
is also a very powerful connection of, you know, there's a power
even though, you know, of the ברית brit being reinforced when they're
actually in the land, which is where they're supposed to sort of
establish it, right? Which is remember the גמרא Gemara had before that
while they were crossing the ירדן, Yarden, יהושע Yehoshua sort of made
them take an oath, like, you know, and that's the important idea,
you know, that you're that you're obligated and that you're you're responsible,
you know, for for each other. And that's of course I think
the point about doing this this whole thing on הר גריזים Har
Gerizim and הר עיבל Har Eval is because this is going to
define what your presence in the land means. So there is a
real power of making one of the three בריתות britot not just
prior but actually about entering, you know, into the land itself. Again,
the benefit of having them all prior is it's all during this
sort of miraculous direct divine connection period, you know, that exists prior
to them entering the land. And again, that's consistent with רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. In ערבות מואב, Arvot Moav, you're just marching orders, those
are instructions. Right? This one's really emphasizing שכר ועונש.
schar ve-onesh. The ברכות brachot and the קללות klalot aspect. Yeah, that's
true too. I mean, although the ברית brit in the the ברית
brit in ערבות מואב Arvot Moav was שכר ועונש schar ve-onesh as
well. Right? Right? I mean, so that was, you know, that ended
with all the ברכות brachot and the קללות klalot there, you know,
so but
that's a very good point, also, to get to added.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara gets into some math, let's skip
let's sort of let's do this. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
ועל כל כל דבר מצוה ומצוה שכתובה בתורה נכרתו עליה ארבעים ושמונה
בריתות. ve'al kol kol dvar mitzvah u'mitzvah she'ktuvah baTorah nichratu aleha arbaim
u'shmonah britot.
So now, once we get 48, somehow the math worked out that
you have because you have 16 times 3, right? Because three בריתות,
britot, that's 48, okay? And that applies now to every individual מצוה.
mitzvah. Okay, so רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda
omer, so now you do 48 times 613. We're not done. רבי
שמעון בן יהודה איש כפר עכו אומר משום רבי שמעון אין לך
מצוה ומצוה שכתובה בתורה שלא נכרתו עליה ארבעים ושמונה בריתות של שש
מאות אלף ושלשת אלפים וחמש מאות וחמשים. Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda ish
Kfar Akko omer mishum Rabbi Shimon ein lecha mitzvah u'mitzvah she'ktuvah baTorah
shelo nichratu aleha arbaim u'shmonah britot shel shesh me'ot elef u'shloshet alafim
v'chamesh me'ot v'chamishim. That's how many, you know, men there were there
in the counting.
So you take that number, 300 and whatever it is, how much
is it? שלשת shloshet and whatever it is, 300 and what, 630,
603,550. Okay, and every single person accepted those 48, so that's the
total number. Now, that's the total number for all the people individually,
but still for each person, it's still 48. Or 48 per מצוה.
mitzvah. אמר רבי, Amar Rabbi, or לדברי רבי שמעון בן יהודה איש
כפר עכו שאמר משום רבי שמעון אין לך כל מצוה ומצוה שבתורה
שלא נכרתו עליה ארבעים ושמונה בריתות של שש מאות אלף ושלשת אלפים
וחמש מאות וחמשים, lidivrei Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda ish Kfar Akko she'amar
mishum Rabbi Shimon ein lecha kol mitzvah u'mitzvah shebaTorah shelo nichratu aleha
arbaim u'shmonah britot shel shesh me'ot elef u'shloshet alafim v'chamesh me'ot v'chamishim,
according to that, there's 48 times
3 603,000. נמצא לכל אחד ואחד מישראל, nimtza le-chol echad ve-echad mi-Yisrael,
so for every individual, שש מאות אלף ושלשת אלפים וחמש מאות וחמשים,
shesh me'ot elef u'shloshet alafim v'chamesh me'ot v'chamishim, there's a 300 603,000.
So what's he saying? So the גמרא Gemara is going to say,
מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? What's what's the difference between these two? אמר
רב משרשיא Amar Rav Mesharshaya ערבה, arva, whether it's ערבות arevut being
a
guarantee... וערבה דערבה איכא בינייהו ve'arva de'arva ika beinayhu and a guarantor
for the guarantor. So what does it mean? It means the first
one was not just saying that, oh, so every person has 48
per מצוה, mitzvah, so let's multiply the total number of בריתות brisos
for the total number of people. No, what it's saying is you
don't just have 48. You have you every individual has 48 for
each מצוה, mitzvah, we're not even we're not even multiplying by 613,
for each מצוה mitzvah you have 48 times 603,000. Wait a minute,
how do I have 48 times 603,000? You know why? Because you
have ערבות arvus for everybody else. So I am חייב chayav for
your 48 and I am חייב chayav to be responsible for your
48 and for your 48, so for every other person, so it's
actually it's minus one, but okay. So if you saw this you
know you know one of those things where you make a lot
of dots and then you have to draw all the lines of
connection in every dot, like it's exponential. Anyway, so each person has
their 48 and has everybody else as ערבות arvus for everybody else's.
So each person has 48 times 603,000.
Right, that's the ערבות. arvus. Now, one also wants to say ערבות
ערבות מרובה arvus arvus meruba anyway. The other is fine, but you
know what? I'm not only responsible, David, for your keeping your 48
בריתות brisos for your 613 מצות. mitzvos. I'm also responsible for your
being for your keeping your ערבות arvus obligations to everyone else. So
since you have 600,000 ערבות arvus obligations times for anyway I'm חייב
chayav for for that. So 600,000 times 600,000,
you do the math. Okay, anyway. Well yeah I mean that's three
levels, I guess that's already too meta. That's already אל תגזים. al
tagzim.
600,000 is how many people there they're saying that's
how many people there were, how many men of that age, right,
that were counted.
So yeah, I did a little throwaway line.
I think it's really the ערבות מרובה arvus meruba line? Absolutely. Yeah,
you like that.
I absolutely otherwise why would רב משרשיא Rav Mesharshaya come in and
build on that? Right.
100%. Yeah, yeah. Thank you. Alright.
And you multiply that
by
613 מצות, mitzvos, you get 10 to the 16th. Alright, תוספות Tosafot
does some of the math. I sort of lost track already. Alright,
moving on. Okay. דרש רבי יהודה בן נחמיה מתורגמניה דרבי יהושע בן
לוי. darash Rabbi Yehuda ben Nechemia meturgamania d'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. Rabbi
Yehuda ben Nechemia, the translator of Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, right, and
that means like the מתורגמנא, meturgamana, the announcer, where anyway but he
anyway he said the following: כל הפרשה כולה לא נאמרה אלא במנאף
ומנאפת. kol haparsha kula lo neemra ela b'mnaef u'mnaefet. The entire ברכות
וקללות brachos u'klalos were only talking about an adulterer and adulteress. So
again tying us back to a סוטה Sotah theme and it's all
about sex
and interestingly though again about the man sinner as well, not just
the woman, focus on the woman. ארור האיש אשר יעשה פסל ומסכה.
arur ha'ish asher ya'aseh pesel u'masecha. So ארור, arur, is he right
to not just curse somebody who is עובד עבודה זרה? oved avoda
zara? I mean, what you know what does that mean? אלא זה
הבא על הערוה והוליד בן, ela zeh habah al ha'erva v'holid ben,
so it's all about sex. It means you didn't actually worship עבודה
זרה, avoda zara, but somebody had sex with a forbidden relationship which
presumably, רש"י Rashi emphasizes we mean adultery, not just one of the
other עריות, arayos, והוליד בן v'holid ben and as a result of
that there was a child and the child is a ממזר. mamzer.
So child isn't accepted in בני ישראל. bnei yisrael. So what does
he do? והלך לבין עובדי כוכבים, v'halach l'vein ovdei kochavim, so fine,
he goes to the non-Jews, the idol worshippers, ועבד עבודה זרה, v'avad
avoda zara, and he worships עבודה זרה avoda zara and that's all
your fault because of your act of adultery. So it all goes
back to the act of adultery. So ארור האיש אשר יעשה פסל
ומסכה arur ha'ish asher ya'aseh pesel u'masecha שכן גרמו לו. sheken garmu
lo. Okay, so that's explains the the case about the about the
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. How do you explain all the ארורs arurs
connected to adultery? So take a quick look at רש"י, Rashi, okay,
במנאף ומנאפת b'mnaef u'mnaefet about 12 lines 4th lines down why, רש"י
Rashi says, I'm sorry, אלא זה הבא על הערוה, ela zeh habah
al ha'erva, that רש"י, Rashi, אשת איש והוליד ממזר מתוך בשתו שעשו
לו לבין עובדי כוכבים ואינו מוצא אישה אלא הוא הלך לבין עובדי
כוכבים ועובד עבודה זרה. eshet ish v'holid mamzer m'toch bushto she'asu lo
l'vein ovdei kochavim v'eino motzei isha ela hu halach l'vein ovdei kochavim
v'oved avoda zara. Okay, ארור האיש אשר יעשה פסל ומסכה. arur ha'ish
asher ya'aseh pesel u'masecha. וכן דורש את כולם כל התלוי לפי פשט
של סוטה של עריות, v'chen doresh et kulam kol hataluy lefi pshat
shel sotah shel arayos, כגון שוכב עם חותנתו ואשת אביו ואם אחותו
כולם באשת איש. kegon shochev im chotanto v'eshet aviv v'em achoto kulam
b'eshet ish. So it wouldn't just be the עריות arayos because he
says the emphasis here is to make it all about adultery. Fine,
we'll add adultery. Those are at least sexual sins. Okay.
Okay, ומכה בסתר ארור, u'makeh baseter arur, שוכב עם בהמה, shochev im
behema, so what's that case? אשת איש שעשה מעשה בהמה, eshet ish
she'asa ma'aseh behema, we get back to that thing about the
סוטה, Sotah, מעשה בהמה, ma'aseh behema, שמנאפת. she'mnaefet. מקלל אביו ואמו, mikalel
aviv v'imo, so what's that case? הבא על אשת איש מזלזל באביו
ואמו שגדלו גדולי רעים בביתם. habah al eshet ish m'zalzel b'aviv v'imo
she'gidlu gidulei ra'im b'veitam. So you know so so you know people
curse your father and mother of the sinners that you could have
made so you know produced a son that would have done this
terrible sin that would have committed adultery or daughter. משגה עור mashgeh
iver who mislead the blind, מפתה יצר, m'fateh yetzer, that's מפתה אשת
איש, m'fateh eshet ish, the guy who seduces the married woman. So
now it's taking away some agency from the woman. No, it's always
two sides of the coin. So the woman isn't necessarily the big
sinner here, it's the man, but takes away some of her agency.
But anyway the man who seduces the married woman, that's לפני עור,
lifnei iver, שיסומא בדבר ואינו יודע עונשו כמוהו, she'isuma badavar v'eino yodeia
onsho kamohu, she does not she doesn't fully understand the weight of
the מצות mitzvos as much as the man. So obviously lots to
unpack here. משיג גבול רעהו, masig gvul re'ehu, how about that? Comrade
going into somebody's, crossing a boundary or whatever, taking away. So בעל
אשתו, ba'al ishto, הרי זה harei zeh הסיג גבול, hesig gvul, you
know, he took.
So that's woman as property. Woman as property. He okay, מכה רעהו
בסתר makei re'ehu basater שגורם לו בלחש she'goreim lo belachash
שתסרח she'tisrach שתמות בבדיקת מים המרים. she'tamus b'vdikas mayim hamarim. So בסתר
basater means that you cause the working of the water to affect
the woman.
לוקח שוחד להכות נפש. loke'ach shochad l'hakot nefesh. What's that? לוקח שוחד
להיות אוהב אחר המנאף loke'ach shochad lihiyot ohev achar hamina'eif ופוסל לו
אשת איש. u'fosel lo eshes ish. So you hire somebody, takes a
bribe, to go ahead and, you know, and help him seduce women
וגרם לו מיתה. v'garam lo misa. Okay. מטה משפט גר יתום, mateh
mishpat ger yatom, איני יודע לדרוש. eini yodeia lidrosh. That's such a
great job! You can't get the last one to fit into this
record. It's all about adultery, okay? Oh, it's all about adultery. Let's
just, I know we're done but we're just going to read to
the Mishna, go very quickly. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, ונתת את הברכה
על הר גרזים ואת הקללה על הר עיבל. v'nasata es habracha al
har Gerizim v'es haklala al har Eval. מה תלמוד לומר? ma talmud
lomar? אם ללמוד שתהא ברכה בהר גרזים וקללה בהר עיבל, im lilmod
she'tehei bracha b'har Gerizim v'klala b'har Eval, הרי כבר נאמר אלה יעמדו
לברך את העם על הר גרזים harei kvar ne'emar eileh ya'amdu l'varech
es ha'am al har Gerizim וכתיב ואלה יעמדו על הקללה בהר עיבל.
u'chtiv v'eileh ya'amdu al haklala b'har Eval.
So so it's, we already know that the division. So why does
it say again ונתת את הברכה? v'nasata es habracha? אלא להקדים ברכה
לקללה, ela l'hakdim bracha laklala,
to tell you first you say the bracha and then you say
the klala. הברכה על הר גרזים והקללה על הר עיבל. habracha al
har Gerizim v'haklala al har Eval. יכול כל הברכות קודמות לקללות? yachol
kol habrachos kodmos laklalos? Maybe you first do all the ברוך baruch
and then you do all the ארור? arur? מה תלמוד לומר ברכה
וקללה ma talmud lomar bracha v'klala in the singular. ברכה אחת קודמת
לקללה ואין כל הברכות קודמות לקללות. bracha achas kodemes laklala v'ein kol
habrachos kodmos laklalos. Okay,
so you do ברוך, baruch, you know, ארור, arur, ברוך, baruch, ארור,
arur, ברוך, baruch, ארור. arur. You go through them individually. להקיש ברכה
לקללה l'hakish bracha l'klala
and to connect them. למה לך לומר? lama l'cha lomar? מה קללות
בלויים אף ברכות בלויים, ma klalos b'leviim af brachos b'leviim, because most
of the detail that the Torah gives is for the klala. It
spells out the arurs. Okay, so that, so so the klalos were
with the leviim, the brachos are. מה קללה בקול רם אף ברכה
בקול רם, ma klala b'kol ram af bracha b'kol ram, a loud
voice. וענית ואמרת v'anisa v'amarta indicates a loud voice. מה קללה בלשון
הקודש אף ברכה בלשון הקודש, ma klala b'lashon hakodesh af bracha b'lashon
hakodesh, right, that's how this whole thing started, that it had to
be in Hebrew. ומה קללה בכלל ובפרט, u'ma klala b'klal u'v'frat,
right, the general and the specific. אף ברכה בכלל ובפרט. af bracha
b'klal u'v'frat. ומה קללה אלו ואלו עונים ואומרים אמן, u'ma klala elu
v'elu onim v'omrim amen,
it's not just half that say amen, everybody responds and says amen.
אף ברכה אלו ואלו עונים ואומרים אמן. af bracha elu v'elu onim
v'omrim amen. Look at that! Only one minute over.